"Hey, Scottie."
"Jesus, man."
I believe Christian movies are bad.
I don't mean they're so bad it's good,
...although there are a few of those.
"Word of advice."
"Don't start preaching around here."
I mean bad as in low-quality,
poor execution, and just wrong.
"Yeah, but I'm not sure I can do that."
"I feel like..."
"...God just wants someone to defend Him."
But before you dislike and click away,
allow me to share why I believe that is.
I would like to start off by
establishing film as an art form.
Film is powerful.
As Jason Silva puts it:
"The aesthetic and intellectual power of cinema,"
"...to me seemed like the most
powerful medium in the world,"
"...like there was nothing that existed that was
better conveying the human experience,"
"...particularly the interior human experience
for the point of view of a character,"
"...from the point of view of a person,"
"...the inner subjective life world of the other, as cinema."
"It was just simply the greatest communication
technology that had ever been made."
"You know, you could talk,
you could sing, you could paint."
"Cinema combined all of these and put
you inside of someone else's world,"
"...and so as an engine of empathy,
as a way of stepping outside yourself,"
"...as a way of witnessing someone else's life."
"I just... I was always moved by cinema."
It's more than just pointing a camera at an actor.
It's a director with an idea who
expresses it via cinematographers,
...who use the placement lenses and settings
of the camera in creative, complex ways
...to tell the story visually,
...actors being truthful under imaginary circumstances,
...and editors arranging individual clips
and sequences into a grand story.
All of that and so much more
...is what makes film, film.
It's a creative art form, and I love it.
Unfortunately, the Christian movie
industry takes this art form for granted
...by rushing through it, which results in poor execution.
This video will go into why Christian movies come
across as Sunday sermons masquerading as movies.
"God sent Jesus to die on the cross
and take the punishment for your sin,"
"...because He loves you."
Now I know that not all Christian
movies are guilty of this.
There are some really good ones.
'Risen' (2016) had the best depiction of Jesus,
'Passion of the Christ' (2004) was beautifully made,
'Believe Me' (2014) is a hilarious
and entertaining eye-opener,
However, I'm afraid there aren't as many good Christian
movies as there are good Christian songs.
A huge majority of these movies just aren't believable,
...but no one is saying anything about this.
I understand Jesus said to speak with love,
...but I don't think that means never
critique anything because it's mean.
As a child, I always disliked this
quote from 'Bambi' (1942):
"If you can't say something nice, don't say nothing at all,"
...because if nobody ever said anything constructive,
...which many people take as mean,
...nobody would get better.
I believe the silence has gone on for long enough.
The only way to improve is to notice your mistakes.
If someone is arrogant of their
mistakes, they will not improve.
One of the infamous things Christian
movies are known for is their low quality.
You can usually tell just by looking at them.
I originally thought this was due to their small budgets.
The Christian movie industry is mainly
independent, or so I thought.
When I watched 'God's Country' (2012),
...I debated incorporating it into this video
because I thought it had a really low budget.
I mean, look at this.
...but I was shocked to find out it had a budget of...
"One million dollars!"
Now that is still considered a small
budget when it comes to movies,
...but for something of this quality?
There are movies with budgets way
smaller that look and sound better.
Money does not equal quality.
"Whoo!"
"Paris Hilton ain't got nothin' on you, girl!"
If you're interested in seeing how much money
Christian movies make (which is a lot),
I have a link to a video in the description
that goes into that in detail.
Money isn't the problem,
...it's the execution.
I have said previously:
Cinematography, an actor's performance, or a
composer's score should all help tell the story.
Here's an example of storytelling through editing.
In this scene from 'Whiplash' (2014),
a film about a passionate jazz drummer,
...the main character is on a first date.
They exchanged some lines of dialogue
about themselves, and then he asks,
"What do you do?"
"I go to Fordham."
"What do you study?"
"I don't... have a major yet."
"But like, what do you want to study?"
"I don't really know."
"I don't know yet."
"So Fordham is just like a random school?"
"No, I applied to a bunch of
schools and Fordham let me in."
"Why did you pick Shaffer?"
"It's the best music school in the country."
Did you catch that?
Let's pay attention to the shots.
At the start of the scene, we are
given an establishing shot,
...which gives us information about the
venue, and where he is, and where she is.
Once they start talking, we cut to
a closer shot of the individual.
Here, they engage in small talk
about what they have in common.
Then he asks this question:
"What do you do?"
Now it cuts to a close-up.
In film language, when it cuts to a
close-up, that means it's important.
That applies to this, but it also tells us
they're getting closer with each other,
...until:
"Why did you pick Shaffer?"
"It's the best music school in the country."
Now we cut back to the medium shot,
...and then back to the establishing shot.
It's awkward between them now.
You can watch this scene with the sound off and
still understand what is happening just by the cuts.
That is good visual storytelling.
Let's watch a scene from a Christian movie.
"Yeah."
"That's Christmas."
"Don't- don't... did..."
"I love...."
"...your sister."
"I love her to death."
"She loves- she loves doing this- she loves..."
"...to put all the lights up, and..."
"...Tariff Act? Which..."
"Anyone? Raised or lowered?"
"Raised"
"...tariffs in an effort to collect more
revenue for the federal government."
"Did it work? Anyone? Anyone know the effects?"
How boring?
Shot reverse shot.
This isn't the result of a low budget.
This is the result of laziness.
Good editing can be achieved by a
13-year old with a phone and iMovie.
It doesn't take any money to edit like that.
What it does take is creativity
and a love for the art form.
Now I brought this up in Part 1, but I'll say it again.
If Christians believe in a limitless, creative God,
...then why are we making unimaginative
movies of such low quality?
Money is not the problem.
They have plenty of it.
The problem with Christian movies is that
they seem to be made by preachers,
...not filmmakers.
"There's two men named
Alex and Stephen Kendrick."
"They make movies:"
"Courageous (2011),"
"...Facing the Giants (2006),"
"...Fireproof (2008)."
"Whether you like their movies or not is not the point."
"These men are preachers."
"They are not filmmakers."
"They will tell you, I know them.
I have worked with them."
"They will tell you, 'We are not here to make art.'"
"'We are not here to make movies.'"
"'We are here to build up the body and
preach the gospel, we use film to do it.'"
"As a result they are gaining influence."
"Where? Not in arts entertainment."
"They are gaining influence in religion."
"They have great favor in arts, but their..."
"...influence is in religion,"
"...because that is their calling."
"It's not about one being right
and the other being wrong."
"Bad art happens when we misidentify our calling."
"They know their calling and they're sticking with it."
In essence, Christians like the Kendrick
Brothers are not filmmakers.
They are basically preachers who
use film to send their message.
I understand and respect that.
Once we approach these as sermons and not as
movies, we can see the message more clearly,
...If there even was one in the first place.
But if these are sermons,
...then what are they preaching?
I believe preachers and filmmakers
have something in common:
To show the truth.
"We know the air is unfit to breathe
and our food is unfit to eat,"
"...and we sit watching our TVs while
some local newscaster tells us"
"...that today we had fifteen homicides
and sixty-three violent crimes,"
"...as if that's the way it's supposed to be."
"We know things are bad — worse than bad."
"They're crazy."
"It's like everything everywhere is going
crazy, so we don't go out anymore."
"We sit in the house, and slowly the
world we're living in is getting smaller,"
"...and all we say is, 'Please, at least
leave us alone in our living rooms."
"Let me have my toaster and my TV and my
steel-belted Radials and I won't say anything."
"Just leave us alone.'"
"Well. I'm not going to leave you alone."
"I want you to get MAD!"
This is where Christian movies,
specifically Pure Flix, gets it wrong.
"I feel like..."
"...God wants someone to defend Him."
Who was 'God's Not Dead' made for?
Let's entertain the thought that it was made for atheists.
Christians already know God's not dead, right?
Do you think an atheist is going
to convert after watching it?
I believe not.
Here's why.
How does 'God's Not Dead' depict atheists?
"There is a god and yep, I'm him."
"I have cancer."
"This couldn't wait till tomorrow."
"Grow up, Amy."
"Nina. This wine is awful."
E P I C S L A P
"I hate God!"
"But I actually believe in God."
"All I have for him is hate!"
"She's a work in progress."
"We're going to prove once and for all..."
"...that God is dead."
"You know what hate is, Tom?"
"I'm not talking about the fairy-tale
stuff, I mean real hate."
"I hate what people like your clients stand for."
"If you ask me, the religious extremists
that we need to worry about"
"...are the hardcore Christians."
"As Socrates put it over 2,000 years ago,"
"'Gnothi seauton'."
"Looks like it's Greek to her."
They depict them
...as the most self-centered, inconsiderate, greedy, uncompassionate human beings on the planet.
Now, how do they depict the Christians?
Well, they're the happiest group of
understanding, loving, caring, perfect people.
But, in my own experience, and in the
experience of many people I know,
...it is actually quite the opposite.
So, how is an atheist going to take 'God's Not Dead'?
Most likely as fake and disingenuous.
It's honestly disrespectful.
It's the equivalent to slapping someone and saying
how righteous you are that you don't slap people,
...immediately after slapping them.
By the way, I'm not saying,
"What could happen if atheists see it?"
Many have actually seen these
movies, and they laugh at it.
Not for being Christian,
...but by single-handedly insulting
an entire group of people.
If it's not made for atheists, then
it's for Christian families, right?
I don't even believe Christian families
should watch these movies.
Here's why.
What these movies depict is not true at all.
If you show these movies to a young child,
...they're going to grow up thinking that
all atheists are the scum of the Earth.
Trust me, I know. I am proof of it.
I grew up watching Christian movies,
...and thought it was my job to disprove every
atheist by arguing in YouTube's comment sections.
Once I realized not every atheist
was out to stray me from my faith,
...I felt incredibly stupid and humbled.
These movies don't encourage you to think for yourself.
They have to tell you what to think,
in order to be a good Christian.
They treat you like a child, having to hold your hand
and explain to you what to think and how to feel,
...which I find disrespectful.
If I recall, didn't Jesus leave a lot of
room for his audiences to think?
That's what makes His teaching so memorable.
You learn better via personal experience,
...rather than someone just telling you.
Another thing that is not true is the situations
where the characters have to defend their faith.
The "Christian persecution" in
these movies doesn't exist.
"If you ask me, the religious
extremists we need to worry about"
"...are the hardcore Christians."
If you want to see a movie on real Christian
persecution, go watch 'Silence' (2016).
It's an amazing film for Christians,
especially missionaries.
But about those cases of the credits?
Not a single one of the cases shown in the
credits have anything to do with the movie.
As a matter of fact they do more harm
than good once you actually research them.
Most of them are just about gay
wedding cakes and birth control,
...two things the movies never go into.
There are more videos and articles that go into
the improbability of the legality of these movies
The links for those are down in the description.
Some would argue that the movies don't actually
have any negative impacts on Christians,
...but I've seen firsthand that that
just simply is not the case.
You see, a couple years ago,
I went to a Newsboys concert.
Right before they played the song 'God's Not Dead',
they showed clips from the movie.
But whenever the atheist was on screen,
...they booed, no matter what he said.
Whenever the Christian was on the screen,
...they cheered.
The atheist would return,
...and so with the booing.
It felt like the two-minute hate
from George Orwell's novel '1984'.
Imagine for a second an atheist teenager
who was invited to a Newsboys concert.
During the concert, he'd be singing to himself.
He might just start believing in Christ.
And then all of a sudden, a bunch of Christians boo
...at who he is.
Would he think Christians are
loving and not judgmental?
Before I end this video, I'd like to show
you a movie called 'Inherit the Wind'.
Released in 1960,
...'Inherit the Wind' is about a teacher who
teaches evolution in a small conservative town,
...and ends up getting taken to court and having to
defend his beliefs against an old hateful Christian.
Sound familiar?
The message of these two movies
is not about science or even God.
It's us
...or them.
Why as Christians do we feel the need to demonize
those who believe differently than us?
Last I checked wasn't Jesus against
the whole 'us or them' mentality?
Should Christians support this?
Let me first ask you this:
Would you support a Sunday sermon
that taught you that atheists are evil
...and it's your job as a perfect Christian to argue with them, victimize yourself, and defend your beliefs,
...even though they were never
attacked in the first place?
That God can't defend Himself
and needs you to do it for Him,
...and that you're not a Christian if you think otherwise?
Whether or not these are the intentions
of Pure Flix is beyond me.
This could all be one big misunderstanding.
However, the impressions these
movies have made still stands.
As fans continue to support
these movies free of criticism,
...Pure Flix will continue to make
movies free of critical thinking.
The problem with most Christian
movies is that they aren't movies,
...they're video sermons.
Now whether or not you agree with
the sermons is entirely up to you.
That's between you and God.
I'll get out of here and let you think for yourself.
Thanks for watching.